<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Dernière modification
     le       $Date$
     par      $Author$
     révision $Revision$ -->
<!-- SAS 20060914 : Relecture initiale -->

<refentry id="app-pgresetxlog">
 <indexterm zone="app-pgresetxlog">
  <primary>pg_resetxlog</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <refmeta>
  <refentrytitle><application>pg_resetxlog</application></refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo>Application</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>

 <refnamediv>
  <refname>pg_resetxlog</refname>
  <refpurpose>réinitialiser les WAL et les autres informations de contrôle d'une
   grappe de bases de données <productname>PostgreSQL</productname></refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>

 <refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
   <command>pg_resetxlog</command>
   <arg choice="opt"><option>-f</option></arg>
   <arg choice="opt"><option>-n</option></arg>
   <arg rep="repeat"><replaceable>option</replaceable></arg>
   <arg choice="req"><arg choice="opt"><option>-D</option></arg> <replaceable class="parameter">rép_données</replaceable></arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>
 </refsynopsisdiv>

 <refsect1 id="r1-app-pgresetxlog-1">
  <title>Description</title>
  <para>
   <command>pg_resetxlog</command> efface les journaux d'écritures anticipées
   (<foreignphrase>Write-Ahead Log</foreignphrase> ou WAL) et réinitialise
   optionnellement quelques autres informations de contrôle stockées dans le fichier
   <filename>pg_control</filename>. Cette fonction est parfois nécessaire si ces
   fichiers ont été corrompus. Elle ne doit être utilisée qu'en dernier
   ressort quand le serveur ne démarre plus du fait d'une telle corruption.
  </para>

  <para>
   À la suite de cette commande, le serveur doit pouvoir redémarrer. Toutefois,
   il ne faut pas perdre de vue que la base de données peut contenir des
   données inconsistantes du fait de transactions partiellement validées.
   Il est alors opportun de sauvegarder les données, lancer
   <command>initdb</command> et de les recharger. Après cela, les inconsistances
   doivent être recherchées et le cas échéant corrigées.
  </para>

  <para>
   Seul l'utilisateur qui a installé le serveur peut utiliser cet outil.
   Il requiert, en effet, un accès en lecture/écriture au répertoire
   des données. Pour des raisons de sécurité, <command>pg_resetxlog</command>
   n'utilise pas la variable d'environnement <envar>PGDATA</envar>. Le répertoire
   des données doit donc être précisé sur la ligne de commande.
  </para>

  <para>
   <!-- ICI -->
   Si <command>pg_resetxlog</command> se plaint de ne pas pouvoir déterminer de
   données valides pour <filename>pg_control</filename>, vous pouvez malgré
   tout le forcer à continuer en spécifiant l'option <option>-f</option>
   (force). Dans ce cas, des valeurs probables sont substituées aux données
   manquantes. La plupart des champs correspondent mais une aide manuelle
   pourrait être nécessaire pour le prochain OID, le prochain TID et sa date,
   le prochain identifiant multi-transaction et son décalage, l'adresse de
   début des journaux de transactions. Ces champs peuvent être configurés en
   utilisant les options indiquées ci-dessus.  Si vous n'êtes pas capable de
   déterminer les bonnes valeurs pour tous ces champs, <option>-f</option>
   peut toujours être utilisé mais la base de données récupérée doit être
   traitée avec encore plus de suspicion que d'habitude&nbsp;: une sauvegarde
   immédiate et un rechargement sont impératifs. <emphasis>Ne pas</emphasis>
   exécuter d'opérations de modifications de données dans la base avant de
   sauvegarder&nbsp;; ce type d'action risque de faire empirer la corruption.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>Options</title>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-f</option></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Force <command>pg_resetxlog</command> to proceed even if it cannot determine
      valid data for <filename>pg_control</filename>, as explained above.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-n</option></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The <option>-n</option> (no operation) option instructs
      <command>pg_resetxlog</command> to print the values reconstructed from
      <filename>pg_control</filename> and values about to be changed, and then exit
      without modifying anything. This is mainly a debugging tool, but can be
      useful as a sanity check before allowing <command>pg_resetxlog</command>
      to proceed for real.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-V</option></term>
    <term><option>--version</option></term>
    <listitem><para>Display version information, then exit.</para></listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-?</option></term>
    <term><option>--help</option></term>
    <listitem><para>Show help, then exit.</para></listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
   The following options are only needed when
   <command>pg_resetxlog</command> is unable to determine appropriate values
   by reading <filename>pg_control</filename>.  Safe values can be determined as
   described below.  For values that take numeric arguments, hexadecimal
   values can be specified by using the prefix <literal>0x</literal>.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-c</option> <replaceable class="parameter">xid</replaceable>,<replaceable class="parameter">xid</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the oldest and newest transaction IDs for which the commit
      time can be retrieved.
     </para>

     <para>
      A safe value for the oldest transaction ID for which the commit time can
      be retrieved (first part) can be determined by looking
      for the numerically smallest file name in the directory
      <filename>pg_commit_ts</filename> under the data directory.  Conversely, a safe
      value for the newest transaction ID for which the commit time can be
      retrieved (second part) can be determined by looking for the numerically
      greatest file name in the same directory.  The file names are in
      hexadecimal.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-e</option> <replaceable class="parameter">xid_epoch</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the next transaction ID's epoch.
     </para>

     <para>
      The transaction ID epoch is not actually stored anywhere in the database
      except in the field that is set by <command>pg_resetxlog</command>,
      so any value will work so far as the database itself is concerned.
      You might need to adjust this value to ensure that replication
      systems such as <application>Slony-I</application> and
      <application>Skytools</application> work correctly &mdash;
      if so, an appropriate value should be obtainable from the state of
      the downstream replicated database.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-l</option> <replaceable class="parameter">xlogfile</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the WAL starting address.
     </para>

     <para>
      The WAL starting address should be
      larger than any WAL segment file name currently existing in
      the directory <filename>pg_xlog</filename> under the data directory.
      These names are also in hexadecimal and have three parts.  The first
      part is the <quote>timeline ID</quote> and should usually be kept the same.
      For example, if <filename>00000001000000320000004A</filename> is the
      largest entry in <filename>pg_xlog</filename>, use <literal>-l 00000001000000320000004B</literal> or higher.
     </para>

     <note>
      <para>
       <command>pg_resetxlog</command> itself looks at the files in
       <filename>pg_xlog</filename> and chooses a default <option>-l</option> setting
       beyond the last existing file name.  Therefore, manual adjustment of
       <option>-l</option> should only be needed if you are aware of WAL segment
       files that are not currently present in <filename>pg_xlog</filename>, such as
       entries in an offline archive; or if the contents of
       <filename>pg_xlog</filename> have been lost entirely.
      </para>
     </note>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-m</option> <replaceable class="parameter">mxid</replaceable>,<replaceable class="parameter">mxid</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the next and oldest multitransaction ID.
     </para>

     <para>
      A safe value for the next multitransaction ID (first part) can be
      determined by looking for the numerically largest file name in the
      directory <filename>pg_multixact/offsets</filename> under the data directory,
      adding one, and then multiplying by 65536 (0x10000).  Conversely, a safe
      value for the oldest multitransaction ID (second part of
      <option>-m</option>) can be determined by looking for the numerically smallest
      file name in the same directory and multiplying by 65536.  The file
      names are in hexadecimal, so the easiest way to do this is to specify
      the option value in hexadecimal and append four zeroes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-o</option> <replaceable class="parameter">oid</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the next OID.
     </para>

     <para>
      There is no comparably easy way to determine a next OID that's beyond
      the largest one in the database, but fortunately it is not critical to
      get the next-OID setting right.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-O</option> <replaceable class="parameter">mxoff</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the next multitransaction offset.
     </para>

     <para>
      A safe value can be determined by looking for the numerically largest
      file name in the directory <filename>pg_multixact/members</filename> under the
      data directory, adding one, and then multiplying by 52352 (0xCC80).
      The file names are in hexadecimal.  There is no simple recipe such as
      the ones for other options of appending zeroes.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><option>-x</option> <replaceable class="parameter">xid</replaceable></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Manually set the next transaction ID.
     </para>

     <para>
      A safe value can be determined by looking for the numerically largest
      file name in the directory <filename>pg_clog</filename> under the data directory,
      adding one,
      and then multiplying by 1048576 (0x100000).  Note that the file names are in
      hexadecimal.  It is usually easiest to specify the option value in
      hexadecimal too. For example, if <filename>0011</filename> is the largest entry
      in <filename>pg_clog</filename>, <literal>-x 0x1200000</literal> will work (five
      trailing zeroes provide the proper multiplier).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>Notes</title>

  <para>
   This command must not be used when the server is
   running.  <command>pg_resetxlog</command> will refuse to start up if
   it finds a server lock file in the data directory.  If the
   server crashed then a lock file might have been left
   behind; in that case you can remove the lock file to allow
   <command>pg_resetxlog</command> to run.  But before you do
   so, make doubly certain that there is no server process still alive.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>See Also</title>

  <simplelist type="inline">
   <member><xref linkend="app-pgcontroldata"/></member>
  </simplelist>
 </refsect1>
</refentry>
